Guide to the Eleanore Collins Papers WAG.089
Tamiment Library and Robert F. Wagner Labor Archives
Eleanore Collins Papers
1944-1993
Tamiment Library and Robert F. Wagner Labor Archives
Collins, Eleanore, -1994
Communications Workers of America. Local 1153 (Valhalla, N.Y.)
Communications Workers of America. Local 1150 (New York, N.Y.)
Kennedy, James R.
Kennedy, Kathy
WAG.089
2.75 Linear Feet in 3 boxes and 2 folders
Eleanore Collins (d. 1994) had a passionate concern for labor education, women's rights, and white-collar organizing. As a clerk with the American Telephone and Telegraph Company (AT&T), she joined the Communications Workers of America (CWA), Local 1150, and by the early 1950s she became a steward. In the CWA, Collins was active in organizing, upgrading clerical titles, and boosting the status and pay for female workers. She served as a union board member, convention delegate, education director, and finally president of the CWA, Local 1153 from 1981 to 1984. The collection includes correspondence, election materials, minutes, arbitration awards, clippings, and reports that reflect both Collins's duties as a CWA local officer and her personal political and community interests.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Eleanore Collins donated 80 colors slides in December 1992 and one linear foot of her papers in 1993. After her death in 1994, more materials were donated by Mr. and Mrs. James Kennedy, Eleanore Collins's niece and her husband. The accession numbers associated with these gifts are 1993.001, 1993.007, and NPA 2000.258.
Conditions Governing Access
Materials are open without restrictions.
Historical/Biographical Note
Eleanore Collins (d. 1994) was born in the Bronx and raised in Elmsford, NY. She graduated from Mount St. Vincent College and later earned a master's degree in industrial labor relations from Pace University. After working briefly for Reader's Digest and then as a social worker, she took a job as a clerk for the American Telephone and Telegraph Company (AT&T) in Manhattan on the eve of World War II. In the early 1950s, she joined the Communications Workers of America (CWA), Local 1150. In 1954, Collins's clerical job was transferred to White Plains, NY. There she became a steward and was active in organizing and upgrading clerical titles. Thanks in large part to her efforts, AT&T created the new title of Engineering Associate, representing a substantial boost in status and pay for a female-dominated classification.
Collins was elected to Local 1150's Executive Board and soon became known for her passionate concern for labor education, women's rights, and white-collar organizing. However, on two occasions, during a bitterly contested Local 1150 election and during the equally rancorous telephone strike, she came into conflict with members of her own and other CWA locals. Controversy over disputed election results in CWA Local 1150's 1958-1959 election occasioned a disciplinary hearing against Eleanore Collins in 1960. In 1971, Collins supported a move by fellow co-workers to return to work at a time when the validity of the picket lines was in question. Other Local members accused Collins of defying union directives. In both cases, charges against Collins were later dismissed.
In 1975, Collins joined with a group of White Plains members who broke away from Local 1150 to form a new CWA local, Local 1153. She went on to serve Local 1153 as a board member, convention delegate, education director, and finally as president from 1981 to 1984.
In the later years of her career, Collins's concern with union activities and efforts to aid in worker security was inclined toward securing pensions and health benefits for employees and retirees. This concern extended to all those in need of health care, with an emphasis on senior citizens.
Collins died in St. Louis, MO in June 1994.
Scope and Content Note
The collection contains correspondence, election materials, minutes, arbitration awards, clippings, and reports that reflect both Collins's duties as a CWA local officer and her personal political and community interests. Ranging from the political to the personal, these papers offer alternative insights into union activities than the insights offered in the official documentation of the CWA.
Collins's union activities with CWA, Local 1150 (and later Local 1153) document important work-related issues as well as broader issues of social policy. For example, the cases of co-workers for whom Collins served as a steward highlight issues of gender and racial discrimination, as well as sexual harassment. In addition, the papers record the shifts in the nature of the female workforce in the telephone industry, which experienced a post-World War II boom due to technological advances and structural changes.
A significant amount of material in the collection deals with the impact of AT&T's divestiture during the mid-1980s. Documents concerning divestiture represent the efforts and positions of the CWA at the international as well as the local level. Several files offer statistical analysis on the impact of divestiture in terms of job loss and other issues of concern to the union.
A major aspect of Collins's work was her involvement with labor education. She taught at local community colleges, as well as in union-sponsored seminars, and her work is documented through course descriptions, syllabi, lecture notes, stewards' training materials, and lesson plans.
Collins was an active participant in many of the CWA's local elections. Information concerning Collins's campaigns, as well as those of her opponents, is well represented in the collection. The types of election materials present, which mostly date from 1978 to 1988, include handbills, flyers, biographies of the candidates, opposing literature, petitions, vote tallies, and special election editions of newsletters.
The collection also documents the Local 1150 election in 1958-1959 and the telephone strike of 1971. Included in the documentation of the 1958-1959 election debate is the trial transcript. Background material detailing the charges brought against Collins and the disputed electoral results constitute one folder. Collins's handwritten notes during the trial on her stance on the 1971 CWA strike against AT&T, as well as the other materials used for her defense, highlight the the debate over local versus national authority in regards to the picket lines.
An undated file marked "Writings" contains typescript essays written by Collins on subjects such as women's employment in the White Plains unit of ATT, job losses in White Plains, and the telephone strike of 1971 in the New York area.
Collins's interest in securing workers' pensions and health benefits, especially for senior citizens, is reflected in her involvement with the Bronx Community Board 12's Health and Hospital Committee and the Westchester Health Action Committee. The collection also documents Collins's service with the White House Conference on Balanced National Growth and Economic Development in 1978.
The collection includes thirteen black-and-white photographs, all group shots or portraits of Collins and other unidentified individuals. There is also a postcard depicting the business district of Valhalla, New York and an undated delegate ribbon with a CWA pin attached to it.
Arrangement
Folders are arranged alphabetically.
Related Material at the Tamiment Library and Robert F. Wagner Labor Archives
Communications Workers of America, Local 1150 (WAG 059)
Communications Workers of America, Local 1153 Records (WAG 132)
Communications Workers of America Oral History Collection (OH 026), which contains transcripts of two interviews conducted with Eleanore Collins in 1991
Newsletters of the Communications Workers of America, Local 1150 from 1952
Newsletter of the Communications Workers of America, Local 1153 from 1984
Labor unions -- Telecommunication -- New York (State) -- New York.; Reports.; Women's rights -- United States.; Women labor leaders |z New York (State); Typescripts; Collective bargaining -- New York (State); Strikes and lockouts -- Telephone companies -- New York (State); Minutes (administrative records); Photographs.; Correspondence.; Clippings (information artifacts); American Telephone and Telegraph Company; Communications Workers of America. Local 1153 (Valhalla, N.Y.); Communications Workers of America. Local 1150 (New York, N.Y.); Collins, Eleanore, -1994; Kennedy, James R.; Kennedy, Kathy
- Address Lists, undated (Box 1, Folder 1)
- Adult Education, 1972-1973 (Box 1, Folder 2)
- AT&T Benefits, 1988 (Box 1, Folder 3)
- AT&TCOM Bargaining, 1985-1989 (Box 1, Folder 4)
- AT&T Job Briefs, undated (Box 1, Folder 5)
- AT&T Job Descriptions, 1986-1989 (Box 1, Folder 6)
- AT&T Managed Health Care, 1990 (Box 1, Folder 7)
- AT&T Retirees Benefits, 1984 (Box 1, Folder 8)
- AT&T Telephone Concession Service, 1983-1986 (Box 1, Folder 9)
- Bell System: Training Material, 1968-1970 (Box 1, Folder 10)
- CWA 36th Convention Color Slides, 1974 (Box Shared Tamiment A006, Folder 1)
- CWA Arbitration, 1951-1952 (Box 1, Folder 11)
- CWA Arbitration, 1972 (Box 1, Folder 12)
- CWA Arbitration, 1978 (Box 1, Folder 13)
- CWA Bargaining, 1986 (Box 1, Folder 14)
- CWA Bargaining, 1989 (Box 1, Folder 15)
- CWA Long Lines Bargaining Unit, 1962-1964, 1970 (Box 1, Folder 16)
- CWA Military Leave of Absence, 1957 (Box 1, Folder 17)
- CWA Racial Discrimination Case, 1984 (Box 1, Folder 18)
- CWA Sales Specialist: Job Classification, 1979 (Box 1, Folder 19)
- CWA Sales Specialist: Job Classification, 1980-1981 (Box 1, Folder 20)
- CWA Sexual Discrimination Case, 1990 (Box 1, Folder 21)
- CWA 1971 Strike (Box 1, Folder 22)
- CWA Local 1150 Arbitration, 1976 (Box 1, Folder 23)
- CWA Local 1150 Arbitration, 1986 (Box 1, Folder 24)
- CWA Local 1150 Clerical Salary Treatment: Affirmative Action, 1972 (Box 1, Folder 25)
- CWA Local 1150 Correspondence, 1953-1970 (Box 1, Folder 26)
- CWA Local 1150 Election, 1958-1961 (Box 1, Folder 27)
- CWA Local 1150 Election, [1962] (Box 1, Folder 28)
- CWA Local 1150 Election, 1972 (Box 1, Folder 29)
- CWA Local 1150 Election, undated (Box 1, Folder 30)
- CWA Local 1150 Engineering Associates: History of Title, 1952 (Box 1, Folder 31)
- CWA Local 1150 Engineering Associates: Job Description, 1962-1964 (Box 1, Folder 32)
- CWA Local 1150 Engineering Associates: Job Description, 1965-1973 (Box 1, Folder 33)
- CWA Local 1150 Engineering Associates: Job Titles and Bargaining Unit, 1962-1965 (Box 1, Folder 34)
- CWA Local 1150 Grievances, 1958-1977 (Box 1, Folder 35)
- CWA Local 1150 Job Upgrades, 1944, 1952, 1966 (Box 1, Folder 36)
- CWA Local 1150 Leaflets, 1962-1963 (Box 1, Folder 37)
- CWA Local 1150 Proposed By-Laws, 1960 (Box 1, Folder 38)
- CWA Local 1150 Trial Boards, 1971 (Box 1, Folder 39)
- CWA Local 1150 Trial Transcript 1st Session, 1960 (Box 1, Folder 40)
- CWA Local 1150 Trial Transcript 2nd Session, 1960 (Box 1, Folder 41)
- CWA Local 1150 Trial Background material, 1960 (Box 1, Folder 42)
- CWA Local 1153 Arbitration, 1987 (Box 2, Folder 1)
- CWA Local 1153 Bargaining, 1986 (Box 2, Folder 2)
- CWA Local 1153 Correspondence, 1979-1981, 1985-1988 (Box 2, Folder 3)
- CWA Local 1153 Election, 1978 (Box 2, Folder 4)
- CWA Local 1153 Election, 1981 (Box 2, Folder 5)
- CWA Local 1153 Election, 1984 (Box 2, Folder 6)
- CWA Local 1153 Election, 1986 (Box 2, Folder 7)
- CWA Local 1153 Election, 1988 (Box 2, Folder 8)
- CWA Local 1153 Election, undated (Box 2, Folder 9)
- CWA Local 1153 Finances, 1980-1981 (Box 2, Folder 10)
- CWA Local 1153 Financial and Advisory Ethics Committee, 1976-1980 (Box 2, Folder 11)
- CWA Local 1153 General, 1976 (Box 2, Folder 12)
- CWA Local 1153 Grievances, 1990 (Box 2, Folder 13)
- CWA Local 1153 Job Losses, 1978 (Box 2, Folder 14)
- CWA Local 1153 Job Losses, 1979 (Box 2, Folder 15)
- CWA Local 1153 Job Losses, 1983 (Box 2, Folder 16)
- CWA Local 1153 Job Losses, 1985 (Box 2, Folder 17)
- CWA Local 1153 Job Losses, 1986 (Box 2, Folder 18)
- CWA Local 1153 Job Losses, 1987-1988 (Box 2, Folder 19)
- CWA Local 1153 Job Losses, 1989 (Box 2, Folder 20)
- CWA Local 1153 Job Losses, 1990 (Box 2, Folder 21)
- CWA Local 1153 Legislative: Human Rights, 1978 (Box 2, Folder 22)
- CWA Local 1153 Pensions, 1981-1985 (Box 2, Folder 23)
- CWA Local 1153 Picnic (Police Dispute), 1984 (Box 2, Folder 24)
- CWA Local 1153 Workers Compensation Seminar, 1987 (Box 2, Folder 25)
- Counseling, 1985-1987 (Box 2, Folder 26)
- Engineering Associates, 1985 (Box 2, Folder 27)
- Engineering Associates, 1988 (Box 2, Folder 28)
- Escorts Arbitration Award, 1967-1985 (Box 2, Folder 29)
- Engineering Associates: Downsizing, 1984 1988 (Box 2, Folder 30)
- Folk Art, 1989 (Box 2, Folder 31)
- The Future of Labor and Employment Law Paul Weiler, [1988] (Box 2, Folder 32)
- Grievances Collins, Eleanore, 1977 (Box 2, Folder 33)
- Grievance Foster, Betty, 1989-1992 (Box 2, Folder 34)
- Health and Hospitals Committee-Bronx Community Board 12, 1986-1987, 1991 (Box 2, Folder 35)
- Health and Hospital Committee Report, 1991 (Box 2, Folder 36)
- Health Coalition Action Group, 1989 (Box 2, Folder 37)
- International Workers of Long Lines, undated (Box 2, Folder 38)
- "Justice" Button-National Labor Relations Board, 1986 (Box 2, Folder 39)
- Labor Education General, 1971-1975 (Box 2, Folder 40)
- Labor Education Lecture Notes, undated (Box 2, Folder 41)
- Legislative General, 1975-1976, 1992 (Box 2, Folder 42)
- Mayer, Henry(CWA Dissidents), 1958 (Box 2, Folder 43)
- Merit Grievances, 1966-1967 (Box 2, Folder 44)
- Merit System Study, 1967 (Box 2, Folder 45)
- Mobilization, 1988 (Box 2, Folder 46)
- Myerscough, George T., 1977 (Box 2, Folder 47)
- Newman Club, 1957 (Box 2, Folder 48)
- New York State Democratic Committee Women's Division, 1985-1990 (Box 2, Folder 49)
- New York Downstate CWA Council, 1965 (Box 2, Folder 50)
- Personal Collins, Eleanore, undated (Box 2, Folder 51)
- Photographs and Delegate Ribbon, circa 1954, 1990-1991, undated (Box Shared Tamiment A003)
- Pioneers, 1987-1988 (Box 2, Folder 52)
- Press Clippings, undated (Box 2, Folder 53)
- Quality of Work Life, 1982-1986 (Box 2, Folder 54)
- Senior Contract Specialist: Job Description, undated (Box 2, Folder 55)
- Sexual Discrimination, 1983 (Box 2, Folder 56)
- Sexual Harassment, undated (Box 2, Folder 57)
- Speeches, undated (Box 2, Folder 58)
- Steward Training Class, undated (Box 2, Folder 59)
- Unfair Dismissal Case: Wansi, Emmanuel, 1991-1993 (Box 3, Folder 1)
- Steward Training Class, 1984, 1988 (Box 3, Folder 2)
- Steward Training Class Manual, undated (Box 3, Folder 3)
- United Way, 1976 (Box 3, Folder 4)
- Westchester Health Action Committee, 1992 (Box 3, Folder 5)
- White House Conference on Balanced National Growth and Economic Development, 1977-1978 (Box 3, Folder 6)
- White Plains, 440 Hamilton Avenue, 1985 (Box 3, Folder 7)
- White Plains Organizing Committee, undated (Box 3, Folder 8)
- Women in Unions, 1974 (Box 3, Folder 9)
- Writings, undated (Box 3, Folder 10)